Austin M. Shearin

https://www.linkedin.com/in/austin-shearin/

Summary

Data scientist/engineer with demonstrated leadership capabilities, 7 years industry work experience, and a strong applied physics and materials science background education. Experience includes establishing extract, transform, load (ETL) processes on-premises and in the cloud, deploying web applications for data management and analysis, and developing custom models for unique datasets. Highly skilled solutions architect with demonstrated performance on several types of projects with various data sources from static files to IoT sensing systems.

Education

M.S. in Materials Science

GPA: 3.97

Missouri State University, Springfield, MO

B.S. in Physics/Materials Physics, magna cum laude

GPA: 3.89

Missouri State University, Springfield, MO

Work Experience

SynTouch, Inc.

Director of Data Science

2022 - Present

December 2014

May 2016

- Work directly with customers to deliver solutions to haptics related issues
 - $\circ\, Design\ experimental\ studies\ to\ collect\ relevant\ data$
 - o Perform analysis utilizing statistics, machine learning, and/or modeling
 - o Deliver reports containing actionable insights and recommendations
- Define the functionality of next generation software solutions
 - o Established a new revenue stream for the company by developing and deploying multiple web-based applications to assist customers
 - o Established a cloud-based infrastructure capable of connecting test equipment to a centralized resource for data transport and analysis
- Mentoring and coaching of fellow software developers

Brewer Science, Inc.

Associate/Sr. Device Systems Engineer – Team Leader

2018 - 2022

- Lead a team consisting of data scientists, data engineers, electrical engineers, and front-end developers
- Team focus was on commercialization of IoT sensor systems which transmit data to the cloud to provide actionable feedback to a customer
- Project manager and principal investigator of several projects including gas, water, and temperature sensing for Industrial Internet of Things and environmental monitoring
- Worked with customers, beta phase partners, and joint development members
- Projects include data transport, management, storage, analysis, and interpretation utilizing modeling and machine learning to perform process monitoring and predictive forecasting

Research Associate II/III

2016 - 2018

- Performed designed experiments to improve sensor performance
- Lead process engineering efforts to increase manufacturing reliability
- Developed novel testing methods to characterize printed sensors
- Implemented automated test systems to collect sensor data
- Utilized first physical principles to perform root-cause analysis

Cell: 417-631-3636

Email:

austinmshearin@gmail.com

Technical Certifications

Python Programmer Track DataCamp

Software engineering, unit testing, parallel processing

<u>Data Analyst with Python Track</u> DataCamp

Data import, export, transport, cleaning, formatting, explorative data analysis

<u>Data Scientist with Python Track</u> DataCamp

Relational databases, hypothesis testing, machine learning

<u>Statistical Thinking for Industrial</u> Problem Solving

SAS

EDA, DOE, quality methods, correlation/regression, statistics

PM Frameworks

Agile Scrum Kanban

Technical Skills

Python	••••
Microsoft Office	•••••
SQL	•••••
SSH/FTP/SFTP	•••••
Technical Writing	••••
Version Control/Git	•••••
Machine Learning	••••
Statistics	••••
Amazon Web	
Services	
Docker	••••
JMP/JSL	••••
Design of	
Experiments	
AutoCAD	•••00
Electrical	
Measurements	•••00
Physical Vapor	
Deposition	
Spectroscopy	•••00
Microscopy	•••00
Crystallography	•••00

Austin M. Shearin

https://www.linkedin.com/in/austin-shearin/

Work Experience Continued

Missouri State University

Per Course Instructor

2019

• Instructed Introduction to Physics I (PHY 123) course and lab

Graduate Research Assistant

2014 - 2016

- Obtained the NASA-MOSGC fellowship for M.S. thesis research project
- Funded research was focused on thin film transition metal dichalcogenide materials with applications in space travel and habitation
- Secondary research projects included metal oxides for renewable energy or drug delivery and nano-bio interactions of graphene with different amino acids
- Mentored undergraduate students in learning different synthesis and characterization techniques

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2011 - 2014

- Assisted graduate students in materials synthesis and analysis techniques
- Exposed to working with metal oxide and nano carbon materials in thin film and nano powder morphology

BearCLAW Math Tutor

2012 - 2014

• Math tutoring of peers from algebra to statistics to differential equations

Wright Patterson Air Force Research Lab

Research Fellow

2015

- Collaborated with resident research scientists to perform research aimed at device development
- Researched interactions between carbonaceous defects and amino acids with applications towards targeted drug delivery and biosensor systems

Research Publications

Anagh Bhaumik, Austin M. Shearin, Rishi Patel, and Kartik Ghosh. Significant enhancement of optical absorption through nanostructuring of copper based oxide semiconductors: Possible future materials for solar energy applications J. Phys. Chem. C. Nanomater. Interfaces 118, 18631–18639 (2014)

A. Bhaumik, A. M. Shearin, R. Delong, A. Wanekaya, and K. Ghosh. Probing the interaction at the nano – bio interface using Raman spectroscopy: ZnO nanoparticles and adenosine triphosphate biomolecules Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys. 16, 11054–11066 (2014)

Presentations in Conferences, Meetings, and Workshops

Nanofrontiers Symposium, 2011, 2012

American Physical Society, 2014

NASA-Missouri Space Grant Consortium Annual Meeting, 2015, 2016

INBRE Conference, 2012, 2013

Argonne National Laboratory Research Symposium, 2012, 2013, 2014

Material Research Society, 2014, 2016

FLEX, 2017

AATCC Textile Discovery Summit, 2022

Cell: 417-631-3636 Email: austinmshearin@gmail.com

References

Dr. Vijaya Kayastha

Device Development Engineer-Team Leader

Brewer Science, Inc.

Cell: 417-343-8096

Dr. Robert Mayanovic

Department Head Missouri State Uni

Missouri State University Department of Physics,

Astronomy, and Materials Science

Office: 417-836-5606

Dr. Kartik Ghosh

Professor & Materials Science Program Coordinator

Missouri State University

Department of Physics,

Astronomy, and Materials Science

Office: 417-836-6205

Dr. David Cornelison

Professor

Missouri State University Department of Physics, Astronomy, and Materials

Science

Office: 417-836-4467